<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The AdaptiveRisk Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/categories/energy/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on The AdaptiveRisk Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/categories/energy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Spot Price Dynamics in Power Markets</title>
      <link>https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/power/spot/2016/07/28/power-spot.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/power/spot/2016/07/28/power-spot.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modelling of spot (daily) prices in commodities usually starts with
modelling monthly average (forward) prices and then selecting some simple
model to describe daily prices within the month relative to the monthly average.
The most common model is a simple Geometric Brownian Motion with constant (spot)
volatility. In this blog post we show that this approach results in wrong
interdependencies (autocorrelation) in spot prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tested two other popular approaches:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;treat daily prices as independent random variables (no autocorrelation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;assume that the spot prices can be described as a mean-reverting process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We show that we should use the
mean reverting process to realistically describe interdependencies of daily
prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The standard approach to modeling daily (spot) prices in commodity markets is to
first model the dynamics of the monthly average (forward) and then generate
daily prices as offsets from this average. Usually monthly forward contracts and
their options have the highest market liquidity so their dynamics can be deduced
quite reliably. Since the forward price is equal to the expected average daily
price, the expectation for the daily offset should be zero. There are two main
approaches to modeling daily prices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;GBM (Geometric Brownian Motion) starting at the level of forward prices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Independent random log-normal variables with means equal to forward prices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These approaches ignore spikes, which are usually accounted by the skew in
volatility constructions. The main difference between these two approaches is
the fact that in the first case the auto-correlation of the daily prices is very
high (since each next step is completely defined by the previous). In the second
approach the auto-correlation is very low, since every day price is completely
independent of previous day prices. This leads to the question we are addressing
with this post: Which model better describes the dynamics of daily prices? We
will consider the case of power prices and will look into data from ERCOT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;daily-dynamics-in-ercot&#34;&gt;Daily Dynamics in ERCOT&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the analysis we used hourly day-ahead LMP prices from a node in the North
Zone of ERCOT. We computed the average of hourly prices over the peak hours (the
hour ending 7am through the hour ending 10pm) and skipped weekends and NERC
holidays. We also computed the monthly average of these prices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/power-spot/prices.png&#34; alt=&#34;power prices&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find which model best describes the behavior of daily prices we ran the
auto-correlation test (
&lt;a href=&#34;https://reference.wolfram.com/language/ref/AutocorrelationTest.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;AutocorrelationTest&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
in Mathematica) on daily prices within each month. Then we found frequency with
which this test declared prices to be autocorrelated. For the peak ERCOT prices
it was 33%. It is a much bigger number than 5%, which we would get if the prices
were independent (we ran the autocorrelation test with 5% significance level)
and it is much smaller than 95%, which we would get if the prices evolve as GBM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this analysis we conclude that neither GBM nor independent variables can
realistically describe the interdependence of daily prices. In the next section
we will discuss a model that produces more realistic results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mean-reverting-daily-prices&#34;&gt;Mean Reverting Daily Prices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many studies used the mean reverting process to describe the dynamics of spot
electricity prices. With discrete time steps the mean reverting process becomes
an AR(1) process with an auto-regression coefficient related to the mean
reversion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\[
\begin{align*}
d\log p_{t} &amp; =\theta\left(\mu-\log p_{t}\right)dt+\sigma dW_{t}\\
\log p_{d+1}-\log p_{d} &amp; =\theta\mu \Delta t-\theta \Delta t\log p_{d}+\sigma\sqrt{\Delta t}\epsilon_{d}\\
\log p_{d+1} &amp; =\left(1-\theta \Delta t\right)\log p_{d}+\theta\mu \Delta t+\sigma\sqrt{\Delta t}\epsilon_{d}
\end{align*}
\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ran the numerical experiment that showed that if we set the auto-regression
coefficient &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\theta \Delta t\)&lt;/span&gt; to 0.33 the frequency with which the
autocorrelation test declared the prices to be autocorrelated was about 33%,
i.e. matched the result for ERCOT daily prices. This suggests that we should use
an AR(1) process to model daily prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analysis in this blog post shows that two basic models describing daily
prices have very different autocorrelation properties - Geometric Brownian
Motion produces price sequences that are perfectly autocorrelated, while
treating prices as independent random variables creates price sequences that are
not autocorrelated. Usually the actual market prices will fall somewhere in
between of these two extremes. The mean reverting model is the simplest model to
accommodate this effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please download the &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/downloads/power-spot.zip&#34;&gt;Mathematica notebook and data&lt;/a&gt;
that were used to obtain the results for this blog post. With this notebook you
can replicate our calculations or play with a different set of parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to leave questions or comments below.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Daily Options</title>
      <link>https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/power/volatility/2016/06/11/daily-opts.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/power/volatility/2016/06/11/daily-opts.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When computing a monthly strip of daily options it is never a good idea to
approximate it with a daily option expiring in in the middle of the month
(15&#39;th day) as errors in value or implied volatility can be as high as 4%.
Instead, it is better to take the daily option that expires after 13.9 days
within a month (this halves the errors of the previous method). An even better
approach would be to take option that expires depending on how far is the
delivery month T - with this method the errors are reduced by a factor of 10
(0.4%). However, this approximation does not work well for deep out of the money
options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daily options are popular contracts in power and natural gas markets.
They are European options where underlyings are daily forward contracts for
the next day after the exercise. In power markets the forward contract can be
peak, off-peak or base load, however in the US only the peak load options are
usually liquid. Usually these options are sold in strips (monthly, quarterly,
annual). When quoting such a strip the price is given as an average option
premium per commodity unit (MWh or MMBtu).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traders judge if an option is too expensive or too cheap by considering its
implied volatility, which is computed using the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_model&#34;&gt;Black model&lt;/a&gt; with a given option
premium and price of the underlying. To find the implied volatility, one has to
solve the following equation for &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\sigma \)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\[ v_{opt}=B\left(T,F,\sigma\right) \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(v_{opt}\)&lt;/span&gt; - option premium,
&lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_model&#34;&gt;Black model&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;em&gt;F&lt;/em&gt; - price of underlying forward. Similarly, in the case of a monthly strip of
daily options one has to solve&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\[
\begin{equation}
  \bar{v}_{opt}=\frac{1}{N}\sum_{i=0}^{N-1}B\left(T + i\Delta t,F,\sigma_i\right)
  \label{eq:strip}
\end{equation}
\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\bar{v}_{opt}\)&lt;/span&gt; - average premium of options in the strip,
&lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; - number of options in the strip, &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; - time to the start of the strip
(start of the month), &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\Delta t\)&lt;/span&gt; - length of one day measured in years,
&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\sigma_i\)&lt;/span&gt; - daily volatility for the &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;-th option in the strip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practice, to speed up calculations, instead of formula (\ref{eq:strip}) one
uses&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\[
\begin{equation}
  \bar{v}_{opt}\thickapprox B\left(T + n\Delta t,F,\sigma_n\right)
  \label{eq:simplified}
\end{equation}  
\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; - some (fixed) day within a strip (say 15&#39;th day if monthly strip is
considered). This approximation speeds up calculations quite significantly
(factor of 30 for a monthly strip). In this blog post we want to investigate
what the best value for &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; is and what the error introduced by this
approximation is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blended-volatility&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;Blended&amp;quot; Volatility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before investigating the approximation described in the
Introduction we need to specify how &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\bar{\sigma}_i\)&lt;/span&gt; are computed. Forward
price dynamics exhibits a term structure of volatility - the farther we are from
the delivery period, the lower the volatility (&amp;quot;Samuelson effect&amp;quot;). Therefore
the volatility of daily prices should be the highest within the delivery month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traders in power markets think about price volatility of daily options in terms
of two periods - before the month starts and inside the month. The volatility
before the month is described by a monthly option (forward volatility), the
market of which is usually more liquid than for daily options. The volatility
inside the month is called spot volatility and describes how daily prices behave
once we are inside the month. Forward volatilities are usually much lower than
spot volatilities. The daily volatilities are then computed by a process that is
called &amp;quot;blending&amp;quot;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\[
\begin{equation}
  \bar{\sigma}_{d}=\sqrt{\frac{\sigma_{F}^{2}T+\sigma_{S}^{2}d\Delta t}{T+d\Delta t}}
  \label{eq:blending}
\end{equation}
\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\bar{\sigma}_{d}\)&lt;/span&gt; - daily volatility for day &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;,
&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\sigma_{F}\)&lt;/span&gt; - volatility of forward contract that expires at time &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;,
&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\sigma_{S}\)&lt;/span&gt; - spot volatility, &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\Delta t\)&lt;/span&gt; - time period spanning one day.
Traders usually assume that the spot volatility is constant throughout the month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;examples&#34;&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our investigation we will make the following assumptions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\sigma_F\)&lt;/span&gt; is constant and equals 30%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\sigma_S\)&lt;/span&gt; is constant and equals 80%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\Delta t\)&lt;/span&gt; is one day expressed in years (i.e. 1/365.25)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a month has 30 days&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we set the interest rate to 0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we set the forward price of commodity to $50 (per unit)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are interested in how the approximation (\ref{eq:simplified}) behaves
for strikes of different moneyness and different times to the delivery month
&lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;. For each case we will present three graphs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First we are going to compute at which value of &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; approximation
(\ref{eq:simplified}) yields equality (i.e. at what value of &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; the option&#39;s
premium equals the average premium of the strip of daily options.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then we compute by how much the approximation is different from the
exact average premium of daily options for a given &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally we compute the spot volatility implied by the approximation and
compare it to the actual spot volatility &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\sigma_S\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will consider only call options (put option results should be similar).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fixed-moneyness&#34;&gt;Fixed Moneyness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consider three cases: at the money &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(K = F\)&lt;/span&gt;, out of the money
&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(K = 1.2\cdot F\)&lt;/span&gt;, and in the money &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(K = 0.8\cdot F\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/daily-options/n-moneyness.png&#34; alt=&#34;n moneyness&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see that when we are close to the delivery month (&lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; is small) the
optimal value of &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; decreases. As time to delivery increases &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; converges to 14.5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;n--145&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 14.5&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we use the value of &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; to which it converges when &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; is large, the
approximation (\ref{eq:simplified}) produces the following errors for value and
implied volatility:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/daily-options/v-moneyness-15.png&#34; alt=&#34;v moneyness 14.5&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/daily-options/vol-moneyness-15.png&#34; alt=&#34;vol moneyness 14.5&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that if &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; is less than about half a year the premium and volatility
errors become big and reach almost 4% at &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; = 2 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;n--139&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 13.9&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can reduce errors observed in the previous section if we pick a smaller value
of &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 13.9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/daily-options/v-moneyness-14.png&#34; alt=&#34;v moneyness 13.9&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/daily-options/vol-moneyness-14.png&#34; alt=&#34;vol moneyness 13.9&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now both premium and volatility relative errors are within 3% for the full
range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;variable-n&#34;&gt;Variable &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can get a better result if we vary &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; with &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;. For this example we set
&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; to be equal to the average of &lt;em&gt;ATM&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;OTM&lt;/em&gt; exact values of &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/daily-options/n-var-moneyness.png&#34; alt=&#34;variable n&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; we get the following results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/daily-options/v-moneyness-var.png&#34; alt=&#34;v moneyness var&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/daily-options/vol-moneyness-var.png&#34; alt=&#34;vol moneyness var&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that at &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; &amp;gt; 1 the errors are essentially 0 and they do not increase
beyond 2% for small &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fixed-reduced-delta&#34;&gt;Fixed Reduced Delta&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results in the previous section show how the error becomes very large
when &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; is small. One reason this happens is that when moneyness is fixed,
delta becomes very small as &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; goes to zero. The intuition here is that
the underlying distribution width is described by variance &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\sigma^2 T\)&lt;/span&gt;.
When the variance is large even large strikes will fall in a very probable
region of the distribution. On the other hand when &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; is small the variance is
small, and even a modest strike can be in a very improbable region of the
distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to describe moneyness while taking into account the above fact is to
use &amp;quot;reduced delta&amp;quot; which is defined as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\[
  D=N\left(\frac{\log\frac{F}{K}}{\sigma\sqrt{T}}\right)
\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure that this &amp;quot;reduced delta&amp;quot; is constant for all &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; we need to adjust
&lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt; as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\[
  K=Fe^{-d\sqrt{T}}
\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt; is some constant. We select this constant to ensure that &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(K/F = 1.2\)&lt;/span&gt;
at 6 months for the OTM case and &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F/K = 1.2\)&lt;/span&gt; at 6 months for the ITM case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/daily-options/n-delta.png&#34; alt=&#34;n delta&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general shapes of the &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; curves are similar to the fixed moneyness case,
but here ATM and OTM curves are identical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The error results when &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; is fixed are similar to the fixed moneyness case
(the errors are somewhat smaller, but not significantly), so we will not show them
here. However, when we vary &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; with &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = average of &lt;em&gt;ATM&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;OTM&lt;/em&gt; exact
values of &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;) we get a much better result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/daily-options/v-delta-var.png&#34; alt=&#34;v delta var&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/daily-options/vol-delta-var.png&#34; alt=&#34;vol delta var&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note how the relative error is now within 0.4% for the full range of &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;case-spot-and-forward-volatilities-are-close&#34;&gt;Case: Spot and Forward Volatilities are Close&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In previous sections we considered the case when the spot volatility is much
larger than the forward volatility (80% vs 30%). But what happens when they
are close to each other? (In reality it almost never happens due to the
Samuelson Effect.) We ran the above analysis for the case when the spot
volatility is just slightly larger than the forward volatility (31% spot vs 30%
forward).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/daily-options/n-spot.png&#34; alt=&#34;n small spot vol&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the shape of the &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; curves is similar to the large spot volatility
case. However, all moneyness cases are now collapsed into a single curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 14.5, to which it converges for large &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;, we get the following
errors for premium and implied volatility:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/daily-options/v-spot.png&#34; alt=&#34;v small spot&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/daily-options/vol-spot.png&#34; alt=&#34;vol small spot&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The errors are very small (within 0.2% for the full range, for both premium and
volatility). If we use 13.9 or variable values for &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; the errors become even
smaller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approximating a strip of dailies with the value of a single daily option is an
efficient technique for significantly increasing the speed of calculation.
However, the time of expiration of the single option needs to be selected
carefully. The usual selection with expiration in the middle of the month is
never optimal and can produce up to 4% errors for the premium or implied
volatility. It is much better to use an option that expires 13.9 days from the
beginning of the month, however the errors in this case are still significant -
2%. The best method is to use an expiration date that changes depending on the
time to delivery month &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;. With this method the errors fall below 0.4%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this approach does not work well for deep out of the money options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can download the &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/downloads/daily-option.nb&#34;&gt;Mathematica notebook&lt;/a&gt; that
was used to obtain the results for this blog post. With this notebook you can
replicate our calculations or play with a different set of parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to leave questions or comments below.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>