<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The AdaptiveRisk Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/tags/derivatives/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on The AdaptiveRisk Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/tags/derivatives/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic</title>
      <link>https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/post/2016-11-26-intrinsic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 00:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/post/2016-11-26-intrinsic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intrinsic value is a well defined and often used concept of option pricing
theory. It is usually defined as the maximum of zero and the value the option
would have if it were exercised immediately. This definition is straightforward
to apply to vanilla option with single exercise decision, but its application to
more complex options traded in energy markets (e.g. natural gas storage or power
tolling) might be confusing. In this blog post we will develop intuition behind
the definition of intrinsic value that will help us understand its importance
and application to complex options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;vanilla-options&#34;&gt;Vanilla Options&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start with discussion of vanilla European call option that expires at time
&lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; with forward delivering at &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; as underlying. I.e. the option gives the
right to option holder to obtain a unit of commodity at time &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; for exchange of
fixed amount equal to strike &lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt;. It is obvious that the option holder would
require to pay some money (option premium) to acquire such an option (the
payout at time &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; for the option holder is always bigger than 0). The option
pricing theory tries to deduce what price option buyer should pay for this kind
of option. Usually the option price depends on time to expiration and properties
of the process by which the underlying prices change. However it is possible to
find a value that does not depend on the dynamics of prices that bounds option
premium from below. One such value we already discussed - it is 0: since the
option payout cannot be negative the price of the option should be positive.
Can we do better than that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more optionality an option provides the more valuable the option is. If we
reduce optionality, the value of the option is reduced. So to find lower bound
of the option we can consider constraining its optionality. We might require the
exercise decision to be made at time &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(t = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;. I.e. at &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(t = 0\)&lt;/span&gt; the option
buyer needs to commit if they receive the unit of commodity at time &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; for
price &lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt;. This certainty allows us (the seller) to setup static hedge that
replicates payoff at &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; perfectly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the buyer decides to exercise we can enter a forward contract that delivers
one unit of the commodity at time &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; for the fixed price (today&#39;s forward rate)
&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{0}\)&lt;/span&gt; (entering such a contract cost nothing at &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(t=0\)&lt;/span&gt;). At time &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; we
will pay &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{0}\)&lt;/span&gt; for the commodity and get &lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt; from the buyer. Our total PnL
is &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(K-F_{0}\)&lt;/span&gt;. Assuming that the interest rate is 0 we would not sell this
contract for less than &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{0}-K\)&lt;/span&gt;, otherwise we would incur losses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the buyer does not exercise we have nothing to do and we can give away such
contract for price 0.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;So the option is exercised when &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{0}-K&gt;0\)&lt;/span&gt;. Then the price is
&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\left(F_{0}-K\right)_{+}\)&lt;/span&gt; which equals to the intrinsic under standard
definition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see that by restricting an option to the immediate exercise we can create a
perfect static hedge that does not depend on the dynamics of the underlying.
The value of the restricted option is the intrinsic value of the original
option. The intrinsic value is always smaller than the value of the original
option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;hedging-and-rolling-intrinsic&#34;&gt;Hedging and Rolling Intrinsic&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By exercising right away and putting static hedge, the option buyer can
eliminate risk at the cost of difference between intrinsic value and full price
paid for the option. So if &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{0}&gt;K\)&lt;/span&gt;, the buyer will enter short futures
position (to sell a unit of the commodity for &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{0}\)&lt;/span&gt; at time &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;). At time
&lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; the buyer will exercise the option and will pay &lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt; for the unit of
commodity which s/he then sells for &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{0}\)&lt;/span&gt;, which in total will produce PnL
equal &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{0}-K\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it possible to improve on this strategy? The simple improvement is called
rolling intrinsic strategy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;At time &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(t=0\)&lt;/span&gt; set up intrinsic strategy (if &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{0}&gt;K\)&lt;/span&gt; short futures, do
nothing otherwise)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If at some future time step &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(0 &lt; t &lt; T\)&lt;/span&gt; the buyer still doesn&#39;t hold short
futures position, look at the futures prices. If &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{t}&gt;F_{t-1}\)&lt;/span&gt; and
&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{t}&gt;K\)&lt;/span&gt; enter short futures position and expect to exercise at expiration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If have short position (say &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{s}\)&lt;/span&gt;, with &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(s &lt; t\)&lt;/span&gt; ) and &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{t} &lt; F_{s}\)&lt;/span&gt;
and &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{t} &lt; K\)&lt;/span&gt; enter long position in &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{t}\)&lt;/span&gt; to clear &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{s}-F_{t}\)&lt;/span&gt; and
do not exercise at &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once at exercise time get &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{s}-K\)&lt;/span&gt; if still hold short futures position.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general the rolling intrinsic can be described as follows: we enter each time
step &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; with a possible hedge which is a set of futures that imply exercise
decision(s). We check if adjusting the hedge to another exercise decision is
profitable - if yes, do that. Notice that this strategy will produce PnL
increasing with time. On different price paths PnL paths will be different.
Also notice that the rolling intrinsic hedge does not work for American type
option, since we used forward contracts with specific delivery time, but
American option does not have one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about total expected (in risk neutral measure) PnL - how is it related to
total option value? As it turns out the expected PnL for rolling intrinsic
strategy is a lower bound for the full value of the option. To see this first
note that in the risk neutral expectation of any portfolio that trades in
forward contracts is equal to 0 (since in risk neutral measure forward rate
equals to expected spot.) So the only way why expected PnL for rolling intrinsic
can be different than the full value of the option if the rolling intrinsic
exercise strategy is different from the optimal exercise strategy. For some
options this is true (for example natural gas storage contract - as discussed in
the next section), however for vanilla option the rolling intrinsic strategy
matches optimal exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that even though exercise policy for rolling intrinsic of vanilla option
matches optimal exercise on each possible path, the PnL will usually be smaller.
Since PnL of vanilla option is always positive we expect that distribution of
PnL of rolling intrinsic of vanilla option will be more narrow than PnL produced
by exercise at expiration. We show this with an example of option with
&lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(F_{0}=3\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(\sigma=0.3\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(T=0.25\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span  class=&#34;math&#34;&gt;\(K=3.1\)&lt;/span&gt; and zero interest rate. We
ran the rolling intrinsic policy with 90 steps and ran 100k simulation paths to
obtain the following results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using Black&#39;s formula the value of the option is 0.1366. MC calculated
expectation of payoff is 0.1351. MC calculated expectation of PnL of rolling
intrinsic is 0.1366. We can see that rolling intrinsic produces value that
matches Black&#39;s formula. It actually produces better result than regular MC
since its distribution is quite more narrow (as we show below).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Examples of cumulative PnL produced by rolling intrinsic hedge is presented on
the following figure. Notice how the cumulative PnL is always increasing and
changes step-wise when exercise strategy changes:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/intrinsic/pnl-paths.png&#34; alt=&#34;rolling intrinsic cumulative PnL&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The standard deviation of unhedged payoff of the option is 0.25. The standard
deviation of rolling intrinsic PnL is 0.14, which is quite significantly smaller
than unhedged case. The hedging effect of the rolling intrinsic can also be
observed on the figure below were we plotted histograms of distributions
ungedged and rolling intrinsic PnLs minus value of the option:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.adaptiverisk.com/images/intrinsic/pnl-distribution.png&#34; alt=&#34;PnL distributions&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see that rolling intrinsic hedge has some nice properties: it does work as a
hedge, PnL path is always increasing, hedging ratios do not depend on
assumptions about dynamics of the process (so the hedge is very robust). However
the hedge is not perfect and it does have significant downside.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>